<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached before the Queen, at White-Hall, upon Friday the 26th of Febr. 1691/2 by W. Talbot ...</title>
            <author>Talbot, William, 1658 or 9-1730.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1692</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62593</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing T123</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R7001</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12918489</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12918489</idno>
            <idno type="VID">95352</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62593)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 95352)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 729:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached before the Queen, at White-Hall, upon Friday the 26th of Febr. 1691/2 by W. Talbot ...</title>
                  <author>Talbot, William, 1658 or 9-1730.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 30 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Thomas Bennet ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1692.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Duke University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Habakkuk I, 13 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:95352:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:95352:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached before the QUEEN, AT WHITE-HALL, Upon <hi>Friday</hi> the 26th of <hi>Febr.</hi> 1691/2.</p>
            <p>By <hi>W. Talbot,</hi> D.D. and Dean of <hi>Worceſter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed by Her Majeſtie's Command.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Thomas Bennet,</hi> at the <hi>Half-Moon</hi> in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard. MDCXCII.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:95352:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:95352:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>HABAKKUK Chap. I. Ver. xiii.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>Thou art of purer eyes than to behold evil, and canſt not look on iniquity; wherefore lookeſt thou upon them that deal treacherouſly, and holdeſt thy tongue when the wicked devoureth the man that is more righteous than he?</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>A Subject, which will almoſt neceſſarily lead our thoughts and meditations to a future Judgment and State, kill our affections and deſires to the empty fading vanities of this World, and raiſe them to the more ſubſtantial and durable ſatisfactions of that which is to come; Teach us a quiet ſubmiſſion to the will of God's Counſels, and engage us to a ſincere obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience to that of his Commands.</p>
            <p>A ſubject, which as it muſt be neceſſary at all times, ſo cannot be unſeaſonable at this; theſe being the great ends which that abſtinence, thoſe pious Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterities which our holy Mother in conformity to pure and uncorrupted Antiquity enjoyns us at this ſeaſon, are deſigned for and ſubſervient to: and theſe will be the proper improvements of my in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Diſcourſe upon the Argument now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore us.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:95352:3"/>
            <p>It is St. <hi>Hierom</hi>'s obſervation in his Preface to his Commentary upon this Prophecy, that the name of <hi>Habakkuk</hi> is derived from a word that ſignifies <hi>Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracing,</hi> and one Notion that he underſtands it in, is the Embraces of a Wreſtler, who claſps his Arms about the perſon he contends with: and in this ſence our Prophet has very emphatically deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved his name, for in this Chapter we have him contending with no leſs an Antagoniſt than the great God, the Lord of Hoſts, and upon no lower a Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject than his Holineſs, Juſtice, and Goodneſs; ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtulating with him about the flouriſhing eſtate and proſperity of bad Men, and the miſeries and afflictions of the Good, as if his permitting there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of were inconſiſtent with thoſe his Glorious At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes; for to that effect he addreſſes himſelf to him in the words I have now read.</p>
            <p>But is it not a very bold and daring thing for a Creature thus to arraign the Juſtice of his Creator; for the thing formed to diſpute with him that formed it, why is ſuch or ſuch a thing ſo or ſo?</p>
            <p>The forementioned <hi>Father</hi> labours to bring the Prophet off, by ſaying, that he does not here ſpeak his own ſence, as if he thought hardly of God for thoſe his Diſpenſations, but in his own perſon repreſents the frailty and impatience of Man.</p>
            <p>Thus much indeed muſt be allowed, that it is not unuſual for holy men in Scripture to ſpeak of others
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:95352:3"/>in the Firſt Perſon, eſpecially when they blame, or reflect upon any fault in them. So St. <hi>Paul</hi> when he had ſpoken ſome things in his own Perſon in the 4th of the 1ſt. to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> expreſly tells them, that he had <hi>in a figure transferr'd thoſe things unto him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf for their ſakes.</hi> And in the 3d. to the <hi>Romans</hi> 7th. ſays he, <hi>If the truth of God hath more abounded through my lye to his glory, why am I judged?</hi> which certainly St. <hi>Paul</hi> never meant of himſelf, but only perſonates an impious Objector.</p>
            <p>But yet, that there is any neceſſity for us with St. <hi>Hierom</hi> to excuſe the Prophet in this place, as not objecting of himſelf, but only urging what Wicked or Atheiſtical perſons might object againſt ſuch a ſeemingly unjuſt diſpenſation, is more than I can ſee: This I am very ſure of, that the beſt of God's ſervants pretend not to Perfection, or to be with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out their Failings, and in this particular caſe before us, we have ſeveral inſtances in Scripture, as we ſhall ſee by and by, of men of no leſs character than <hi>Habakkuk,</hi> who have made the ſame objecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with this in the <hi>Text.</hi> But whether he objects in his own, or in the perſon of another, I will not contend; be that as it will, the caſe was this: He had in the beginning of the <hi>Chapter</hi> complained of the iniquity of the <hi>Jews</hi> for which God threatens from the 5th verſ to bring upon them the <hi>Chaldaeans,</hi> that <hi>bitter and haſty Nation,</hi> as he calls them, and that they
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:95352:4"/>ſhall <hi>march through the breadth of their land, and poſſeſs their dwellings, and lead them away captive.</hi> And then after he had in the 12th. <hi>ver.</hi> deprecated this ſevere Judgment, and begg'd of God not to ſuffer thoſe whom he had from the beginning choſen to be his peculiar people, to come to an utter exciſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; He acknowledges that <hi>Nebuchadonoſor</hi> was raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up by God for a ſcourge to the wicked, ſtrengthened and ſupported by him for the cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection of his Enemies: But yet expoſtulates with him for ſuffering him to ruin, and to grow fat with the ſpoils of thoſe that were not ſo bad as himſelf. As if he had ſaid, True it is, O Lord, we are a very wicked and ſinful people, but yet not ſo bad as the Tyrannous <hi>Nebuchadonoſor,</hi> and his Idolatrous <hi>Chaldaeans.</hi> How then can it be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtent with thy juſtice and hatred to ſin, to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit the greater ſinners to proſper in their oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the leſs, of thoſe that are better than them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou art of purer eyes than to behold evil, and canſt not look on iniquity; wherefore lookeſt thou upon them that deal treacherouſly, and holdeſt thy tongue when the wicked devoureth the man that is more righteous than he?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thou art of purer eyes than to behold evil,</hi> this is one of thoſe many condeſcenſions to our infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, which the holy Spirit is pleaſed to make in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:95352:4"/>Scripture when he ſpeaks of God, and means no more, than that ſin is the moſt odious and deteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thing to God that can be, as offenſive to him as thoſe things are to us, which we cannot bear the ſight of.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And canſt not look on iniquity, (i.e.)</hi> thou canſt not abett or approve of it, for ſo the phraſes <hi>to behold, to know, to look on,</hi> do frequently ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie in the Scriptures. <hi>The Lord knoweth the way of the righteous,</hi> ſays <hi>David, (i.e.)</hi> he is pleaſed with, he does approve of it. And <hi>the Lords eyes will behold, or look on the thing that is juſt (i.e.)</hi> with Approbation or Complacency.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherefore then looke'ſt thou upon them that deal treacherouſly?</hi> (i.e.) Why doſt thou favour them with ſucceſs in their treacherous enterpriſes?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And holdeſt thy tongue,</hi> doſt not interpoſe, doſt not hinder the wicked from <hi>Devouring,</hi> Oppreſſing, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlaving, Perſecuting, Murdering <hi>the man that is more righteous than he,</hi> who comparatively with reſpect to the Oppreſſor may be ſaid to be righteous, or at leaſt leſs wicked than he.</p>
            <p>The words thus explained, contain an expoſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation with God, concerning that ſeemingly ſtrange diſpenſation of his Providence in ſuffering the wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to proſper and thrive, and that by the afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and oppreſſions of the Righteous, as if it were a reproach to his Holineſs and Juſtice.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:95352:5"/>
            <p>Which ſince it is the main engine, by which the <hi>Atheiſt</hi> endeavours to batter down the great Doctrine of Providence, and conſequently to render all Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion uſeleſs; (For if God does not concern him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf with Affairs below, if he has no knowledge of what we do, to what purpoſe ſhould we wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip or ſerve him? Then is our Preaching vain, and your Faith and Works vain alſo; then they are not Fools who count our lives madneſs, that wear them out in the ſtrict exerciſes of Watching, and Faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Mortification and Self-denial, but we really are the Fools and Mad men that take ſo much pains, undergoe ſuch ſeverities, renounce the ſatisfactions of the world, deny our appetites, crucifie our fleſh, macerate our Bodies, dye daily, and all for the ſake and ſervice of a Being that knows nothing of all this, from whom therefore we can neither ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect reward for performing theſe ſervices, nor fear to be puniſhed for leaving them undone) I humbly crave leave to conſider it very particularly, and to examine the whole force of it in this method.</p>
            <p n="1">I. I ſhall conſider the ground or occaſion of this expoſtulation in the Text, and of the <hi>Atheiſts</hi> Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jections againſt Providence, <hi>(viz.)</hi> Bad mens flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhing and thriving, and that by their injuring and oppreſſing of Good men, <hi>their devouring thoſe that are more righteous than they.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:95352:5"/>II. I ſhall inquire into the Objections that are made againſt God's permiſſion hereof, and the Atheiſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Concluſions that are drawn from it.</p>
            <p n="3">III. I ſhall attempt a vindication of the Divine Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence, by ſhewing the weakneſs of thoſe Objections, and the unreaſonableneſs of thoſe Concluſions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> I ſhall by way of Application ſhew what more reaſonable Inferences we ought to make from this Diſpenſation, what practical inſtructions it will afford us for the government of our Lives.</p>
            <p n="1">I. For the ground or occaſion of this expoſtulation in the Text, and of the Atheiſts objections againſt Providence, (<hi>viz.</hi>) Bad mens flouriſhing and thriving, and that by their injuring and oppreſſing of good men, <hi>their devouring thoſe that are more righteous than they.</hi> And here I intend not to diſpute the truth of the Sup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, but ſhall very readily allow it, and muſt profeſs my ſelf ſo far from being ſurpriſed or wondring at it, that I ſhould think it very ſtrange if it ſhould be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe; for good men cannot oppreſs, or take in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>direct methods to thrive, they have a God above and a Conſcience within, which overawes them, and will not ſuffer them to do it; nor can they be ſuppoſed to uſe ſuch means as may effectually ſecure them from the violences and oppreſſions of others; for the good man charitably meaſuring others by himſelf, and think<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that they would as little harm him, as he would them, or as he had deſerved from them, does not ſtand upon a conſtant guard, nor uſe preventive methods to keep off thoſe injuries that he is not apprehenſive of;
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:95352:6"/>nor does he when he ſees them coming uſe any force or violence to repel them which may hurt the aggreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſor, but chooſes rather to ſuffer injury than to do it. But now as he lies thus open and defenceleſs, on the other hand a bad man has none of thoſe reſtraints of God, or Conſcience, or Charity to hinder him from falling upon the Prey that lies expoſed to him: Tell him of a God that will execute Vengeance upon the Oppreſſor, and he cryes out with him in the <hi>Pſal. Tuſh, thou God careſt not for it.</hi> If Conſcience ſtir or offer to interpoſe, he rebukes it in the words of the Devils to our Saviour, <hi>Art thou come to torment me before thetime?</hi> And for Charity or doing by others as he would be done by, 'tis a thing that he has no notion of, he is for doing by others, not as he wiſhes or deſires, but as he believes others would do by him. And being very wicked himſelf, he judges all others to be like himſelf, and therefore whatever inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice or villany he intends or is guilty of towards his Neighbour, 'tis no more he apprehends than what, were his and his Neighbour's circumſtances changed, his Neighbour would do to him. And whether he believe ſo or not, his will hath no bounds but his power.</p>
            <p>So that conſidering the natural bent and inclinations of bad men, that they are the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> in the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle</hi>'s phraſe, <hi>thoſe that will be rich,</hi> reſolved upon thri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving and gaining in this world as their great end, and chief good: and with all that they have none of thoſe reſtraints, that good men are under, to check their inclinations, or to hinder them from proſecuting them; and adding to this that the defenceleſs eſtate of the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:95352:6"/>Humble, Meek, Patient, Charitable man does invite and encourage them to fix upon him as their Prey, it is not to be wondred at, that <hi>thoſe that deal treacherouſly proſper,</hi> or <hi>that the wicked devoureth the man that is more righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous than he.</hi> And yet this is the ground of this expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulation with God in the Text, why does he ſuffer it? why does he look on and hold his tongue? And what thoſe Objections are which Wicked and Atheiſtical perſons make againſt his permiſſion hereof, we under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>took in the <hi>Second</hi> place to enquire.</p>
            <p n="2">II. And there is not among all the various diſpenſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of God to the Sons of men, any that bad men have taken occaſion more violently to object againſt than this: For albeit the natural tendency of things, the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guarded condition of the Good; the unreſtrained Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſions of the Bad, make it very probable that things would be thus, were they left to themſelves. Yet how comes it to paſs that God does not interpoſe, that he does not hinder the one, and defend the other? This has been a ſtumbling-block not only to ill men, but to ſome of God's choiceſt Servants, we find them often ſtagger'd at it, and not knowing what to conclude from it. Holy <hi>Job</hi> who is tranſmitted to us as in other re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects, a very great Pattern of Patience, when he ſaw the proſperity of the Wicked, could not contain him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, but cries out in his 21. <hi>Chap. ver.</hi> 4. <hi>As for me, is my complaint to man? and if it were, why ſhould not my ſpirit be troubled? wherefore do the wicked live, become old, yea, are mighty in power,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Jeremy</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſeems to be at a very great loſs how to reconcile
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:95352:7"/>this with God's Juſtice, in his 12. <hi>Chap. verſ.</hi> 1. <hi>Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous art thou, O Lord, when I plead with thee; yet let me talk with thee of thy Judgments,</hi> or let me expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtulate, or reaſon the caſe with thee, <hi>Wherefore doth the way of the wicked proſper? wherefore are all they happy that deal very treacherouſly?</hi> But above all it was the ſoreſt Temptation to the Author of the 73. <hi>Pſalm,</hi> he confeſſes that <hi>his feet were almoſt gone, his treadings had well nigh ſlipt; and why? he was grieved at the wicked, he ſaw the ungodly in ſuch proſperity.</hi> This makes him cry out in the 13. <hi>ver. Verily I have cleanſed my heart in vain, and waſhed my hands in innocency.</hi> Nay it had almoſt prevailed with him to make the ſame con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of it that thoſe wicked ones did, whom he mentions in the 11th <hi>ver.</hi> who inferr'd from it that <hi>God does not know, there is no knowledge in the moſt High.</hi> And at this time, this is the great Argument which the Atheiſt uſes to baniſh the belief of a God and his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence out of the world; For thus he argues from the wicked's oppreſſing and afflicting the pious Servants or God, and proſpering and thriving by it; Either God does not ſee, has no knowledge of theſe things, or if he does ſee and has knowledge of them, he either would hinder them but cannot, or can hinder them but will not; If God would hinder them but cannot, then is he not omnipotent; if he can but will not, then is he not juſt and good; ſo that either his Power or his Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice and Goodneſs muſt be given up, or elſe thoſe At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tributes muſt be ſalved by the Imperfection of his knowledge, and ſo he pretends it a kinder as
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:95352:7"/>well as more reaſonable thing to ſay that God does not regard, is not at leiſure to take Cogniſance of affairs below, rather than that he wants either the power, or juſtice and goodneſs to hinder ſuch irregularities: and thus the knot is cut inſtead of being untied, and the Atheiſt ſeems ſo tender of ſome of God's Attributes as to take thoſe meaſures to ſecure them which would effectually prove him not to be God, which is what he de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to prove; for the true Notion of a God is a Being infinite in all perfections, and that Being that wants any is not God; and therefore he that is defective in knowledge can no more be God, than he that is not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite in Power, Juſtice, or Goodneſs. Thus <hi>theſe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puters of the world, who through wiſdom,</hi> as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſpeaks, <hi>know not God,</hi> by their fooliſh reaſonings would diſpute him out of Being.</p>
            <p n="3">III. But to vindicate the Divine Providence from theſe unreaſonable cavils, and to expoſe the weakneſs of thoſe objections which are made againſt this proce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure (which was the third thing propoſed), I have no more to do than to ſhew that it may be very conſiſtent with the Juſtice and Goodneſs of God to permit theſe things; for the Objection is built upon the contrary ſuppoſition, and the Atheiſt would therefore prove that if there be a God, either he does not know or cannot hinder theſe things; becauſe it is inconſiſtent with his Juſtice and Goodneſs to ſuffer them, if he knows and can prevent them: But now if God may be very juſt and good, notwithſtanding he does ſuffer and can prevent them, then is his permiſſion thereof no argument ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of his want of Knowledge or Power.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:95352:8"/>
            <p>I ſay then God does ſee, has knowledge of theſe things, nay he not only ſees but orders or ſuffers them; for nothing falls out but by his appointment, or permiſſion; all the occurrences in the world are the reſults not of Chance, but of his wiſe Counſel, the effects of that Providence that extends it ſelf to the moſt minute Creature, <hi>not a Sparrow falls to the ground without him, even the hairs of our head are all numbred.</hi> And he can prevent and hinder theſe things if he pleaſes, his power extends to every thing that is the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject of any power, to every thing that does not imply a contradiction.</p>
            <p>But though God does ſee and order, or permit, and can prevent theſe things if he pleaſes, yet is his per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of them not at all inconſiſtent with his infinite Juſtice and Goodneſs.</p>
            <p>For the proof of which I will endeavour to make good theſe three things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That it is not inconſiſtent with God's Juſtice and Goodneſs to ſuffer good men to be afflicted in this World.</p>
            <p n="2">2. That it is not inconſiſtent with God's Juſtice and Goodneſs to ſuffer bad men to be proſperous here.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That it is not inconſiſtent with God's Juſtice and Goodneſs to ſuffer bad men to be the inſtruments by which good men are afflicted.</p>
            <p n="1">I. It is not inconſiſtent with God's Juſtice and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to ſuffer good men to be afflicted in this world, for theſe reaſons.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:95352:8"/>1. Becauſe afflictions in this world are not always puniſhments, but many times excellent means whereby. God deſigns a great deal of good and benefit to thoſe that are exerciſed with them; by which he weans them from the world, reduces them when they are go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſtray, tryes, proves their Faith, Patience, Submiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, Reſignation to, and dependence upon himſelf; by which he advances and increaſes their Graces, raiſes and heightens, their deſires, and longings after that perfect ſtate of unmixt happineſs, where no afflictions can en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: and then when afflictions produce ſuch bleſſed effects, when they yield ſuch <hi>peaceable fruits of righteouſneſs,</hi> certainly God is neither unjuſt nor unkind in ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his beſt Servants to be exerciſed with them. But,</p>
            <p n="2">2. Suppoſing afflictions to be puniſhments, yet let the beſt man that ever labour'd under the ſevereſt of them, but look into himſelf, and he will find abundant cauſe to acquit the Juſtice and Goodneſs of God: for <hi>there is none righteous that ſins not; the juſt man falls ſeven times a day,</hi> the very beſt of meer men have ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny failings, are guilty of many ſins; which, if God ſhould deal rigorouſly with them, would make them juſtly liable to eternal damnation. Is God then unjuſt in puniſhing thoſe that offend, and deſerve puniſhment; in puniſhing thoſe with temporal calamities that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve eternal? Nay, is he not very good and merciful in chaſtiſing them here for their ſins, and not reſerving them for the dreadful Account of the other world? So that conſidering the nature of afflictions, that they are not always puniſhments, and the demerits of the beſt
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:95352:9"/>of men, that though they were puniſhments, yet they deſerve much worſe, it can be no impeachment of God's Juſtice and Goodneſs that he permits good men to be afflicted in this world; eſpecially ſince,</p>
            <p n="3">3. He has appointed a day wherein he will abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly recompence all the troubles and ſorrows and ſufferings of the pious men with joys unſpeakable and full of glory, when all the preſſures and injuries he la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured under here, ſhall add weight and luſtre to that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver-fading Crown which is reſerved for him in the Heavens.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As it is not inconſiſtent with God's juſtice and good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to ſuffer good men to be afflicted, ſo neither is it to ſuffer bad men to be proſperous here. For,</p>
            <p n="1">1. As afflictions are not always puniſhments, ſo proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity is not always a bleſſing; to let a ſinner commit his villanies with impunity, and to be a gainer by them is, it may be, one of the ſevereſt inflictions that God lays upon men in this world; there is not a more dreadful ſentence that God paſſes upon any wretch in this life, than that or ſuch like as he pronounced againſt <hi>Ephraim, Ephraim is joyned to Idols, let him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone,</hi> let him take his courſe, enjoy his beloved Idols, go on merrily in his ſins, he ſhall have no check, or hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derance from me. The ſteps to God's hardning of <hi>Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raoh,</hi> as the Scripture terms it, were the taking off his Judgments from him and his Land; whileſt they were upon him, he promiſes in obedience to the meſſage which <hi>Moſes</hi> brought him from the Lord, to let the people go; the fire of affliction, while he was in it, had ſoft<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned and temper'd him into a compliance with the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Commands: but when he ſaw there was reſpite,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:95352:9"/>the Rod taken off, the Judgments removed, he would not let the people go; when once out of the fire, preſently he returned to his former hardneſs: If then the impunity and proſperity of the wicked be their hardning and Judgment, it is certainly not unjuſt with God to ſuffer it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Suppoſing their proſperity to be a bleſſing to them, yet as there is no good man but has a great Allay of evil mixt with his goodneſs, ſo there is hardly any man ſo bad but has ſomething of good in him, at leaſt ſome natural or moral good, ſome good quality, by which he is uſeful and ſerviceable to the World: Now for God to reward the natural or moral goodneſs of other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe very bad men, with outward temporal bleſſings, ſeems very agreeable to that rule by which he governs himſelf in the diſtributions of recompences, <hi>(viz.)</hi> to reward every one according to his works; and is ſo far from being a reaſonable objection againſt his Juſtice or Goodneſs, that no doubt the Atheiſt would more vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently, and I am ſure, more plauſibly object againſt both, if God ſhould ſuffer that, whether natural or moral goodneſs, to be altogether unrewarded: Beſides, bad men are many times inſtruments in the hands of God for the execution of his purpoſes, and bringing about of his deſigns, and their ſerving the ends of Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vidence (though undeſignedly and unwittingly) God looks upon himſelf in ſome ſort obliged to reward with outward recompences; it was the caſe of <hi>Nebuchadnezar,</hi> of whom (though for his own private ends he had made War againſt <hi>Tyrus,</hi> yet becauſe he did thereby inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentally ſerve to work God's purpoſes againſt <hi>Tyrus</hi> too) God ſays he <hi>will give him the land of Aegypt for his
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:95352:10"/>labour, wherewith he ſerved againſt Tyrus, for he wrought for me, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But 3dly. Although wicked men ſhould have none of this natural or moral goodneſs, nor any uſeful quality to mankind, nor be any ways ſerviceable to the ends of Providence, but were purely bad without the leaſt Allay or mixture of goodneſs, yet certainly it cannot argue want either of Juſtice or Goodneſs in God to trye all means to reduce theſe wicked men and make them bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter. If God ſhould puniſh villany as ſoon as it is com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted, cut the ſinner off in the actual commiſſion of his iniquity, give him no ſpace to repent, nor uſe any methods to bring him to it, the Atheiſt would think this much more cruel and unjuſt. But for God to try whether a ſianer will be reformed or not, before he ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutes judgments upon him, to afford him time and opportunities for repentance, to ſhew ſome outward kindneſs, beſtow ſome temporal good things upon him, to try if happily his mercy will lead him to make uſe of thoſe opportunities, as it is a clear demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtration of the goodneſs of God, ſo is it no argument againſt his Juſtice; Becauſe if theſe methods fail of their deſigned ends, and the ſinner continues proof againſt them, and unreformed by them, there is in the</p>
            <p n="4">4. Place a day of retribution coming, <hi>the day of the revelation of the righteous judgment</hi> of God, when im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety and villany, however it has eſcaped and proſper'd here, ſhall be ſure to meet with its due returns; when God's long abuſed Patience ſhall appeal to his Juſtice, and his Goodneſs that could not lead the ſinner to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, ſhall aggravate his guilt and heighten his con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation.</p>
            <pb n="17" facs="tcp:95352:10"/>
            <p>So that it is no impeachment of God's Goodneſs or Juſtice that he ſuffers very bad men to be proſperous here, becauſe proſperity is not always a bleſſing to them, or if it were, yet poſſibly there may be ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of good in them which God may think fit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward with outward favours, or if they have no good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs in them, his bleſſings to them are but the attempts of his mercy to work ſome in them; and if they prove unſucceſsful, his juſtice ſhall be ſure to be glorified at the laſt in their Eternal deſtruction.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It is not inconſiſtent with God's Juſtice and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs to ſuffer bad men to be the inſtruments whereby good men are afflicted; This ſeems to be the great Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection in the Text, <hi>Why holdeſt thou thy tongue while the wicked devoureth the man that is more righteous than he?</hi> Although a good man may deſerve afflictions, yet certainly he does not deſerve ſo bad as that perſecuting Tyrant, or that cruel Oppreſſor; Why then does that wretch ſucceed in his oppreſſing and injuring of him that is not ſo bad as himſelf?</p>
            <p>But here I hope it will be no difficult matter to clear the Juſtice and Goodneſs of God.</p>
            <p>For if as I have already proved, God may with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the leaſt impeachment of thoſe Attributes lay af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flictions upon the beſt of men, and they have no reaſon to complain of either for his afflicting them, I cannot ſee why he ſhould be cenſured for the means he makes uſe of for the executing thoſe afflictions; nor why he ſhould be thought more hardly of for uſing men for that purpoſe, than for employing any brute inſtrument: If by my ſins I have forfeited his protection, and my title
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:95352:11"/>to my Goods, Eſtate, or Life, I am no more unjuſtly dealt with if he ſuffers a Thief or Plunderer to rob me or pillage my goods, than if he had ſuffered a Fire to conſume them; if he ſuffers a powerful Oppreſſor, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured Evidences, or a corrupt Judge, to take, ſwear, or give away my Eſtate, than if he had ſuffered a ſtorm at Sea, or any accident at Land to ruine me; if he ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers a perſecuting Tyrant, a profligate <hi>Debauchee,</hi> or ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orn'd witneſſes to murder me, than if he had ſuffered any ordinary diſeaſe to have been my death; for both the one and the other are but inſtruments in the hands of God for the execution of his Judgments; and if I have deſerved thoſe Judgments from him by what means ſoever he executes them upon me, I cannot call him unjuſt.</p>
            <p>Yet it ſeems hard that thoſe who have much more deſerved to ſuffer, ſhould fare better than thoſe who have leſs deſerved it, and ſhould proſper and triumph in their ruin.</p>
            <p>But if (as I ſhewed before) this proſperity of the wicked is but their Hardning, their Judgment, whereas all the afflictions they are permitted to exerciſe good men with are but for the purging out of their corrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, the tryals or improvements of their Graces, and advances of their Happineſs, if this be only the wicked's receiving their good things here, of which they muſt expect no portion hereafter, and the righteous receiving their evil things in this world, that ſo they may eſcape the ſeverer retributions of that which is to come, then the wicked oppreſſors do not in the iſſue fare ſo well as then the afflicted righteous.</p>
            <p>Beſides, who elſe can be the executioners of theſe
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:95352:11"/>Judgments but the wicked? Can good men oppreſs, ſteal, perſecute, kill? or would they continue good if they ſhould? None other are capable of being theſe inſtruments but bad men, who can be contented to thrive and gain by any methods, how baſe or wicked ſoever; and who take great delight in any inſtances whereby they may expreſs the enmity that has ſo long been between the ſeed of the Serpent and the Seed of the Woman, and of wreak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing that ſpleen and malice which they the children of the Devil will ever bear to thoſe that are born of God.</p>
            <p>In ſhort, if there be any injuſtice or unkindneſs in God's making uſe of ſuch inſtruments for the execution of his Judgments, it muſt be either with reſpect to the perſons that ſuffer, or to the inſtruments themſelves; It can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be with reſpect to thoſe that ſuffer, who having cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptions enough to need afflictions for Diſcipline, and ſins enough to provoke God's Judgments, he is neither un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt, nor unkind in making uſe of the moſt capable and apt, whether brute or rational Inſtruments, for the laying thoſe afflictions upon them, which they ſtand ſo much in need of, or ſo juſtly deſerve: Nor with rela<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion to thoſe wicked inſtruments; for taking God's per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of their villanies and ſuffering them to proſper and thrive by them in the ſevereſt ſence, yet, if God has tryed, and they have been proof againſt his former methods for their reformation, what injuſtice is there in his giving over to try them any further? Is God ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged to uſe violence to make men good, and to force them to be happy againſt their wills? 'Tis enough that he has placed Heaven and Hell before them, given them their option of Life and Death; that he has waited
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:95352:12"/>long to ſee which they will chooſe, that he has uſed various methods to incline them to make a wiſe choice, and to reclaim them from thoſe wicked courſes which they are engaged in, and which lead to eternal death; if all this will not do, and they will neither be led to repentance by his goodneſs, nor driven by his judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, who can call God unjuſt or unmerciful in ſuffering them at laſt to take their courſe, and to run into that deſtruction which they would not be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuaded to avoid?</p>
            <p>And thus I hope I have ſufficiently proved that it may be very conſiſtent with God's Juſtice and Goodneſs to ſuffer good men to be afflicted, bad men to be proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perous in this world; and likewiſe bad men to be the inſtruments by which good men are afflicted: And if God may be very juſt and good in permitting theſe things, then may he notwithſtanding that his permiſſion, be ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry knowing and powerful too; for his not hindring a thing, which he is juſt and good in permitting, can be no argument of his want either of knowledge of that thing, or of power to prevent it.</p>
            <p>Having now vindicated the Divine Providence from thoſe Objections which the Atheiſt raiſes againſt it, and ſeen the unreaſonableneſs of thoſe Concluſions which he draws from bad mens ſucceeding in their oppreſſions, and thriving with the ſpoils of thoſe that are better than themſelves; I proceed in the laſt place to ſhew what more reaſonable as well as uſeful Inferences we ought to make from hence, and what practical Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions this conſideration will afford us for the govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of our lives. And it will be of very great uſe to
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:95352:12"/>us in theſe following particulars, which I hinted in the beginning.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Since God ſuffers bad men to proſper, and good men to be afflicted in this world, this gives us an irre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fragable aſſurance of a future Judgment and State; be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe otherwiſe there will not be an opportunity to manifeſt that univerſal and impartial Juſtice which is eſſential to the Notion of a God, and which he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantly aſſerts he will govern himſelf by in his diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>butions of Rewards and Puniſhments to the Sons of men, whom he aſſures he will recompence according to their works: For however God may very righteouſly, for the manifeſtation of his goodneſs, and to convince men that not the leaſt good in any ſhall fail of its reward, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence that little goodneſs or ſerviceableneſs that is in bad men with ſome outward proſperity here, ſince there is a Hell prepared for them wherein they ſhall ſuffer the juſt puniſhment of the general impiety of their lives; and for the manifeſtation of his Juſtice, and hatred to ſin puniſh the faults and failings of the beſt men with temporal afflictions, ſince a glorious reward of all their piety and goodneſs is reſerved for them in the other world; yet, if there were no ſuch rewards or puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to be diſtributed hereafter, theſe diſpenſations here would hardly ſeem juſt. As ſure therefore as there is <hi>a God that judgeth in the earth,</hi> and <hi>this Judge of all the world will do right,</hi> ſo ſure, from the miſeries of the good and happineſs of the wicked here, we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude that there will be a day wherein the Scene ſhall be changed, a Judgment that ſhall ſet all theſe things right and ſtraight, ſhall aſſign to the wicked for their
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:95352:13"/>portion an eternity of tribulation and anguiſh and pain; but to the afflicted righteous, glory and honour and eternal life.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Since God permits very good men to be afflicted, and very bad men to flouriſh here, this ſhould teach us that Leſſon of St. <hi>John, not to love this world, nor the things of the world,</hi> for it muſt neceſſarily abate our love and value for the world, to conſider that it is a place where the greateſt innocency and vertue cannot ſecure a man from ſufferings, but poſſibly expoſe him the more to them, where a good man cannot be ſafe, but lies open to the oppreſſions of tyranny and villany, where bad men proſper and <hi>devour thoſe that are more righteous than they,</hi> undoubtedly to a good man this cannot ſeem a deſirable place: And then for the things of the world, by which I mean the enjoyments of it, the Power, the Honours, the Riches, the Pleaſures, from hence we may make a due eſtimate of them too; for certainly we muſt allow that God does beſt underſtand the value of things, but it is very plain from hence that in his eſteem theſe things are not very valueable; for if they were, he would never ſuffer his favourites whom he loves to be without them, and his enemies whom he hates to ejoy them; which ſince he does, it is clear that in his judgment they are of no great worth; and therefore ſhould be of no great account with us, becauſe we are ſure that the judgment of God is according to truth.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Since God ſuffers good men to be afflicted and wicked men to enjoy proſperity in this world, this ſhould excite and inflame our deſires and longings after
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:95352:13"/>the other world, not only becauſe in general that will be a place where the Scene ſhall be ſhifted, where the wicked ſhall be made miſerable, and the good man hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py. A conſideration which does mightily enhance the glorious rewards that attend good men in the other world, and therefore may juſtly raiſe our expectations of them; for from the afflictions which good men labour under here, they may well conclude, That God who ſees and knows them, and cannot forget their labours of love, will not let the ſufferings they undergo for his ſake, to loſe their reward; and indeed they have his promiſe to relie upon, that he will not, for he aſſures them by his <hi>holy Apoſtle,</hi> that <hi>their light afflictions that are but for a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſhall work for them,</hi> not only glory, but, <hi>a far more exceeding and eternal weight of glory.</hi> And as the ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings of good men, ſo the proſperity of bad men here may juſtly heighten our apprehenſions of thoſe glories that are laid up for good men hereafter. For it is very natural to argue, If God be ſo gracious to bad men, ſo bountiful to thoſe that are Baſtards and not Sons, as to indulge them a liberal ſhare of proſperity and the good things of this life; then infinitely great furely are thoſe rewards, and inconceiveably glorious is that inheritance which is reſerved in Heaven for thoſe good men that are his true Sons by Regeneration and Adoption.</p>
            <p n="4">4. What I have diſcourſed ſhould teach us neither to think hardly of God, nor to envy wicked men when he permits them to perſecute his Church, and to triumph in the miſeries and ruin of his beſt Servants. The <hi>Pſalmiſt,</hi> when he had recovered himſelf, owns himſelf to have been <hi>Fooliſh,</hi> and <hi>Ignorant,</hi> and <hi>a Beaſt,</hi> for grieving at the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:95352:14"/>flouriſhing Eſtate of the ungodly, and for entertaining hard and unworthy thoughts of God upon that account; he found upon his going into the Sanctuary that the proſperity of theſe men was but their being mounted higher upon ſlippery places, that they might the more ſurely and irrecoverably fall, and that their end was to be <hi>rooted out</hi> at the laſt: whereas whatever perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutions good men ſuffer, the end of the upright man would be Peace, and therefore he acknowledges that in all theſe ſeemingly unaccountable Diſpenſations, <hi>truly God is loving unto Iſrael.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I am ſure we of this Church and Nation have found him to be ſo, and have reaſon to ſay with one of the famous <hi>Seven Brethren</hi> in the <hi>Maccabees,</hi> that <hi>though the living God has been angry with us for a while for our chaſtening and correction, yet at laſt he has been at one again with his ſervants:</hi> Though he has ſhak'd his Rod over us, threatned to remove our Candleſtick, and to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit our Adverſaries to lay waſt our <hi>Sion;</hi> yet he has put a hook into their Noſtrils, and <hi>ſent his Angels to deliver us out of the hands of our enemies, and from the expectation of all the people that hate us.</hi> And though he has not yet ſo wonderfully appear'd for the reſcue of ſome of our reformed Brethren; whether it be that they are not yet meet for ſuch a Deliverance, or their enemies not ripe for Deſtruction; that theſe have not yet filled up the meaſures of their ſins, nor the other lain long enough under the ſcourge for their correction and reformation, or for whatever other reaſon it pleaſes him ſtill to ſuffer their perſecuting enemies to tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nize over them: yet let us have a care of charging God
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:95352:14"/>fooliſhly for the heavy ſufferings of our Brethren, or of envying the long ſucceſs of their Perſecutors, for <hi>God is juſt in all his dealings, and holy and good in all his ways, he does not afflict willingly nor grieve the children of men,</hi> but when he has great reaſon for it, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent ends to ſerve by it. And however the proſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity of their perſecutors may look to unthinking men, yet to envy it, is indeed to envy them their Judgment and Reprobation; and to ſuffer the utmoſt miſery, the moſt exquiſite torments that the wit or malice of a <hi>Miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſionary</hi> can invent, or the fury of <hi>Dragoons</hi> execute, is ten thouſand times rather to be choſen than to enjoy all the proſperity and ſucceſs, all the pomp and power in the world, and at the ſame time to labour under the guilt of ſo many ſacred Promiſes and Oaths broken, ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſolemn Leagues and Treaties violated, and under the Tears and Cries of ſo many miſerable Orphans and Widows, the unjuſt Invaſions and Deſolations of ſo many Countries and Cities, the Blood of ſo many thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſands, the Rapes upon ſo many Souls as well as Bodies, as the Greateſt Tyrant of this or any Age has to anſwer for. But</p>
            <p n="5">5. And <hi>Laſtly,</hi> from hence we learn alſo that all theſe I have now mentioned and, if poſſible, greater impieties and treacheries in our Adverſaries, will give us no ſecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity againſt them, if we by our ſins provoke God to give us over unto them. Poſſibly ſome of over ſanguine Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexions and hopes may flatter themſelves with great aſſurances of ſafety and ſucceſs meerly from the conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration of the wickedneſs of thoſe Enemies we are ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily engaged with, who it muſt be acknowledged
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:95352:15"/>are ſuch, that if ever the wickedneſs of enemies alone were a ſufficient ground to raiſe a hope of ſucceſs againſt them, we might reaſonably conceive ſuch hopes. But what I have been largely inſiſting on may be ſufficient to arm us againſt ſo fatal a deluſion: For God, I have obſerved, does and may make uſe of what Inſtruments he pleaſes, the vileſt and worſt of men for the execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of his Judgments: and therefore if we by our pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vocations have deſerved ſo ſevere a one, as that our glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhould be given up into our enemies hands, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not from their impiety promiſe our ſelves impunity.</p>
            <p>We muſt not then take our meaſures from them, but turn our eyes inwards, and ſee how things ſtand at home; But, Bleſſed God! what a black and affrighting Scene ſhall we here behold? Should I inſiſt upon the greater light and knowledg of our duty that has been afford<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed us, the ſtricter obligations to it, that our holy Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion lays upon us, the purer way of worſhip that we have been bleſs'd with, and all the various endearing methods that God has uſed to reform and <hi>purifie us to himſelf a peculiar people zealous of good works;</hi> and then inquire how we have anſwered theſe obligations, what effects theſe methods have had upon us? whether we have been as much purer than our neighbours in our lives; as much more reformed in our manners, as our Church and Religion are more pure and reformed than theirs, as much better in every reſpect than they, as we have had reaſon and opportunity to be? ſhould I enumerate the particular ſcandalous vices that are publickly com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted and gloried in, whether thoſe of our own growth, or thoſe we have fetch'd over together with their fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhions
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:95352:15"/>from foreign Nations, and in both outdone our Patterns; ſhould I reflect upon the unthinking life of ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, who are as <hi>without God in the world, for he is not in all their thoughts;</hi> who divide their time between ſleep and pleaſure, and as they never call themſelves to account, ſo they as little conſider that God will: Or upon the more daring provocations of others, who count it the greateſt ſcandal and reproach to be thought Serious and Vertuous, and are afraid of nothing ſo much as the imputation of Sobriety and Religion; who ſhew their Wit, as they vainly think, in ridiculing every thing that is Sacred, and their Courage in defying God, their Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences and the eternal flames that are prepared for them, whether they believe it or not. Should I undertake the melancholick and ungrateful imployment, of ripping up theſe, of laying open that general diſſolution of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners that is too viſible among us to be diſſembled, it would eaſily convince us that we have little reaſon to value our ſelves above our Neighbours, or to think our ſelves <hi>more righteous than they:</hi> But were we ſo, and were they much worſe than we are, as bad almoſt as the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vil himſelf, and as odious in thoſe <hi>pure eyes that cannot look upon iniquity;</hi> Yet as it is no new thing for a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent to correct his Child with that rod which he after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards throws into the fire; ſo neither is it ſtrange or unjuſt with God to make thoſe the inſtruments and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecutioners of his Wrath and Vengeance here, whom he deſigns for the everlaſting Objects of them hereafter: and therefore whilſt our own ſins teſtifie and fight againſt us, 'tis to no purpoſe to hope that the greater faults of our Enemies ſhould be any defence to us.</p>
            <pb n="28" facs="tcp:95352:16"/>
            <p>If ever then we would raiſe to our ſelves any com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortable aſſurances or hopes of being ſaved from our Enemies abroad, we muſt firſt endeavour to be ſaved from our more dangerous ones at home; labouring with all our might, in our ſeveral ſtations and capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, to help forward that great deſign of a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Reformation amongſt our ſelves.</p>
            <p>'Tis a glorious and God-like Work, and however thoſe that engage in it muſt expect the greateſt oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition from the Prince and Men of this world, yet for their encouragement they may aſſure themſelves that greater is he that will be with them, than all that can be againſt them; and though they muſt <hi>wreſtle both againſt fleſh and blood,</hi> the luſts and corrupt affections of men, and alſo <hi>againſt Principalities and Powers, againſt the Rulers of the darkneſs of this world, againſt ſpiritual wickedneſſes in high places,</hi> againſt all the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licy and forces of the Devil and his Inſtruments; yet this ought not to diſcourage them, for they ſhall have the Strength and Wiſdom of Heaven on their ſides, and that <hi>God who has begun a good work by them,</hi> will (I truſt) in his due time bring it to perfection.</p>
            <p>But till this be done by us, or ſeriouſly and in good earneſt endeavoured, <hi>while we hate to be reformed,</hi> what have we do to take this portion of God's word into our mouths, or to apply ourſelves to him in the language of our Prophet? to tell him that <hi>he is of purer eyes than to behold evil, and cannot look upon iniquity?</hi> while we continue evil, and our iniquities are multiplied in his ſight, what is it but either to mock him or tempt him to deſtroy us from before his Face? and while we per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:95352:16"/>in our wickedneſs, and will be unrighteous ſtill, how or with what Face can we, what ever Enemies we ſhould fall a prey to, or however barbarouſly we ſhould be uſed by them, expoſtulate with God, <hi>Why holdeſt thou thy tongue when the wicked devoureth the man that is more righteous than he?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>No, if ever we expect comfort in Contemplating, or ſucceſs in Pleading before God, his holineſs, juſtice and goodneſs, we muſt firſt become holy and juſt and good our ſelves, we muſt break off our ſins by repentance, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vote our ſelves intirely to his ſervice and obedience; and then thoſe Attributes of his will be our ſecurity, under any diſpenſations of his Providence, That the iſſue ſhall be our good and advantage.</p>
            <p>I will not preſume to treſpaſs further than only to ſubjoyn, That this is a very proper and neceſſary work for this time, both as it is that part of the Year which the Church has more particularly devoted to Abſtinence and Mortification; and I am ſure all our Faſtings and Auſterities that do not help us to deny our ſins as well as our Meats and Pleaſures, that do not tend to reform and make us more apt and ready for the work and ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of God, are very vain and to no purpoſe; and alſo as it is the Seaſon wherein we are going out to Bat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tel againſt our Enemies; and if God go not forth with our Hoſts, what ſucceſs can we expect? and how can we imagine that he ſhould come into an Alliance with us, till we have broke our League with Death and agreement with Hell, and diſcarded our ſins, to which he is an irreconcileable Enemy?</p>
            <pb n="30" facs="tcp:95352:17"/>
            <p>Let us <hi>then turn away from all our wickedneſs that we have committed, and do that which is lawful and right, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying all ungodlineſs and worldly luſts and living ſoberly, righteouſly, and godly in this preſent world; let us rent our hearts and not our garments, and turn to the Lord with weeping and faſting and mourning; let the Prieſts, the Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters of the Lord, ſanctiſie themſelves, and weep between the Porch and the Altar, and ſay, Spare thy people, O Lord, and give not thy heritage to reproach, that the heathen ſhould rule over them; wherefore ſhould they ſay among the people, Where is their God?</hi> Let all Orders and Degrees of men among us repent and amend, and then cry mighti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unto God, <hi>Look down, O Lord, from Heaven, and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold from the habitation of thy holineſs and of thy glory; Where is thy zeal and thy ſtrength, the ſounding of thy bowels and thy mercy towards us? Are they reſtrained? O, our Redeemer, ſuffer not our Adverſaries again to tread down thy Sanctuary, the people of thy holineſs have poſſeſt it yet but a little while:</hi> And then we may hope, that God will hear and have mercy; that thus ſowing in Tears we ſhall reap in joy, and that ſuch a penitential Spring will be followed with a happy and ſucceſsful Summer.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:95352:17"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
